chapter 5 is called message passing and
neurobiology
what is your overview thought on chapter
five
okay uh I mean
it's the kind of I don't know I have
mixed feelings about this chapter
because on one hand you see as far as I
understand uh active inference although
it originated as a quote-unquote a
unified theory of the brain I don't
think uh it's a neurobiological theory
per se uh of course there can be some
correlations between a neurobiological
uh components or concepts with active
inference active inference I mean
Concepts but uh I mean it's not uh an
essential premise of active inference
Theory to provide a theory to provide a
comprehensive theory about how the
neurobiology of human brain or other
organisms brain
behave uh at the detailed and neural
anatomical
level but
at the uh then again it's nice to have
these kinds of empirical correlations uh
between the findings of neurobiology and
the active inference uh Theory uh but I
I don't think it's uh one of active
inference
um Central assertions at least uh to my
understanding
well said very interesting framing
well chapter five definitely takes a
very specific system of Interest
approach
by highlighting one of the most studied
areas also one of the most relevant
areas which is
mammalian neuroscience
and the chapter is going to introduce a
few different
motifs in the nervous system
and essentially build up towards figure
5.5 which is at the end of the chapter
and 5.5 wires together three specific
neural systems that the chapter is going
to focus on work in that area from
so Ollie said it very well
active inference was built up to in
chapter four here is another level or
type of science with assertions or with
representations or mappings to any
specific system but this is the kind of
modeling that has been built up and done
by fristin power pizullo and others over
the decades with a focus coming from a
human neural Imaging laboratory setting
a lot of focus and study and attention
and funding and everything on the
mammalian nervous system
but claims about the nervous system have
have uh
are not the basis of what active
inference claims or how it's derived
but this is like an example case study
in neurobiology connecting back to some
of the formalisms that we've just seen
introduced in chapter four
yeah and uh to add a minor Point uh to
which you just said I think it's
important to draw attention to the last
sentence of the last paragraph of the
first page it is important to draw a
distinction between a principle I.E the
minimization of free energy and a
process theory about how this principle
may be implemented in a certain kind of
system so I I think this sentence here
uh frames this chapter in relation to
all the other technical chapters of this
book so if every other chapter is about
developing or at least up to now was
about developing
um
the principled formalism of active
inference now chapter 5 provides a kind
of preliminary sketch for the process
theory of active inference which is uh
obviously far from an extensive Theory
it's just a single chapter but then
again it can provide some important uh
signpost signpost for anyone who wants
to further investigate this area
awesome free energy principle Bayesian
mechanics all things in that area are on
this principle
not responsive to empirical data
and then the process theory is about how
the principle is implemented so the
specific generative models that are made
and how well they map or how well they
do in a portfolio of models that can
have very different goals and
assumptions and all of this
but the process Theory implementation
lets us develop hypotheses that are
answerable to empirical data like
what is the kind of information
or relationship between
photons hitting the retina and
changes in activity in neural systems
and that's an informational question or
can be abstracted in a way to an
informational question that it turns out
does have empirical support and results
in unique explanations and predictions
that doesn't mean that it always results
but a lot of citations are provided here
that's what we can explore in chapter
five
the last paragraph of the first section
describes that they're going to look at
the three different neural systems
okay section 5.2 micro circuits and
messages
what do you think Ali
uh all right so
uh I mean this chapter begins uh from
how a message passing happens in
neurobiological terms
um and compare it to the way active
inference frames this message passing
mechanism and specifically if we look at
uh figure
5.1 and compare this figure to the ones
we've seen before
in chapters uh
one through four I think it was in
chapter four we can see some clear
parallels between how this kind of
cortical message passaging happens in
the brain versus how it is framed in
active inference literature and as we
can see it's uh clearly inspired by the
neurobiology of the brain but then it's
important to keep in mind that it's not
a direct one-to-one mapping between
these two models
this is just um a kind of I don't know
uh an interesting or
Illuminating uh if you like parallel to
keep in mind to somehow be a bit more
confident about the viability of the
theory we want to use for message
passing and active inference uh which is
to say it's not some haphazard Theory
that's just been developed for practical
reasons it has some basis in
neurobiology although uh it's not
necessarily fully congruent with every
detail of neurobiological neurobiology
great the specific example is going to
involve this one region of mammalian
cortex tissue that has these six layers
and there's a ton of neurobiology
the big takeaway for figure 5.1 is that
it's possible to graphically lay out
nodes and variables and find some
empirical
correspondences again some unique
explanations and predictions in certain
cases
and that's one kind of modeling where
it's really trying to understand and
improve the ability to do correlation
and intervention and counter factual
causal type analysis with the real
system of Interest or in a more
pedagogical setting or in a research
setting or an industrial setting you
might sweep across large families of
structures of models and there's no need
to be grounded to any biological
structure at all
so this is just describing the specific
neuroanatomical research that really
arose out of the Imaging work at UCL and
the SPM package so that's where a lot of
this comes from
5.2 yeah good and sorry just as a side
note I think watching uh one of Thomas
parr's lectures on neurobiology of
active inference which is available in
YouTube would really help to understand
the materials of this chapter better so
I highly recommend watching that one
thanks
figure 5.2
gives a re-rendering of a kind of
classical View
of a hierarchical predictive coding
system works
so here abstracting a layer from the
tissue
six layer to just two layers here
computational layers now
and then showing how there's
hierarchical communication within a
layer but also
uh well there's they're signaling within
a layer and there's a hierarchy
uh in Bayesian modeling with variables
that are higher order predictions about
other variables and that's the basis of
the predictive coding architecture
so 5.2 looks at some ways that the
something that resonates with the
cerebral cortical architecture enables
what might computationally look like or
have some really strong
and explanatory values in actually
relating to computationally a
hierarchical Bayesian model which could
do various General tasks
all right 5.3 is motor commands leaving
the prefrontal cortex going down to the
butterfly looking cross section here
what is 5.3
okay so uh 5.3 moves to the other half
of active inference framework which is
uh I mean how how it can model uh the
decision making and uh ultimately uh the
movement of the agent uh in order to
minimize the
expected free energy as opposed to
variation on free energy that we saw in
perceptual uh half of active inference
so
it can provide a kind of uh correlation
or analogy between the structural neural
Anatomy uh particularly related to uh I
mean the motor commands and uh
how it can relate to active inference in
particularly The Continuous time active
inference so
we can see that uh for I mean for the
external uh uh event or I'm sorry for
the external State we can take for
example the proprioceptive afferent and
then uh this proprioceptive afferent
acts as a kind of why or the continuous
time active inference which needs to be
uh
um I mean processed in in a way to
optimize the expected free energy and
how it relates to both attention and
precision uh we will see a bit more
detail about uh those uh those terms and
the relation between them in chapter
eight but I think here section 5.3
provides a good summary about the
general uh paths through the motor
command systems of neurobiology
great let's say while the previous case
study focused on how the connectivity
within in between the cortical columns
could have a computational relationship
with a Bayesian hierarchical predictive
coding architecture
the argument of this second case study
is that a continuous input continuous
output
kind of set point seeking
reflexive motor Behavior
with a moving set point with a
descending moving set point enabling
motion by changing ultimately the set
point
and enabling uh variation in the
strategies to reach that set point
through different mechanisms
this is also describable in a compatible
way
that's a shorter section now section 5.4
subcortical structures
what would you say about this section
okay so subcortical
structures are very important in the the
decision making and and I mean the
planning
of the agents so
uh obviously here we need to uh we need
another kind of analogy between uh the
way
that these plannings and decision
makings happen uh neuroanatomically with
the way uh that uh that it's framed in
active inference but again uh we can see
it's uh clearly based on uh I mean at
least some of the important elements
we've seen from uh the previous chapters
uh so for example we we saw how policy
is described or how how it relates to
outcomes and and preference and so on uh
we can see uh those elements are
directly inspired by a neuroanatomical
structures so
uh
I guess that's uh at least in my opinion
this section here 5.4 uh seems a bit
more uh
sketchy in the meaning that it doesn't
go into quite uh in the extensive
details about how how how those
structures can be
um can be compared about for anyone who
wants to uh
further investigate these topics there
are some useful references put on here
and Pages 93 and 94. so
yeah
thanks yeah it's really abbreviated and
overviewed but
we get an interlude from table 5.1
with putative roles of neurotransmitters
so same perspective that we took before
on neural anatomical functionalism here
directly translates to neurotransmitter
reductionism or essentialism or
something like that so certainly all
neurotransmitters and molecules they
play variable roles in different
settings
and
this is the knee in scruffy
manifold all over again
one person might say well we we need a
theory for every acetylcholine molecule
in the world they're all in a unique
context and someone else says all
neurotransmitters are described by one
parameter in this model I'm getting
value from it so to me that's an account
and somewhere in between is the work in
this space which is making an attempt to
have a principled and falsifiable
approach to
model the computational aspects of
specific regions and contexts and
settings and so acetylcholine
noradrenaline dopamine and serotonin are
given a little mini review here
and so it's not an exhaustive or an
exclusive claim it's kind of a
provocation from computational and
molecular neuroscience and people can
look into the papers and also ones that
probably have been published since
5.6 goes to continuous and discrete
hierarchies
which is graphically overviewed in
figure 5.5 so what would you say about
this
uh yeah one interesting thing about this
section is
um
the observation that
our lower level
engagement with the environment uh it
can be most successfully characterized
with continuous time formulations but as
we go up uh and uh I mean on the level
of uh cognitive Concepts or at the level
of cognitive hierarchies and we come to
Concepts such as I don't know decisions
or even beliefs and so on we can reach
the area that the discrete time
situations uh would probably be more
efficient to uh
to characterize the behavior of the
agent so this multi-scale
um a multi-scale structure of active
inference modeling is quite evident in
the way that our message passing happens
in our brain in terms of our lower level
data processing
up into
consolidating the higher level cognitive
Concepts and ontologies
awesome thank you
to me figure 5.5 demonstrates the kind
of whole of body approach
that you could imagine there's so many
organs and systems and phenomena for
which there aren't specific generative
models so little can be said about
situations where no generative model has
been articulated and here's one where it
has so it gives you also it's kind of
like reading a drosophila melanogaster
review paper
relatively it's like this is how much
work it takes to get to this state of
knowledge in an insect so then in
another insect do we know less about
that insect empirically and genetically
so consider this to be what's known to
be a lot however also about one of the
most sophisticated or specific cognitive
systems at least we know so there's that
additional kind of like self-reflexive
aspect to this chapter
that is not a Cornerstone of active
inference but here it's just presented
in a synthetic case study
anything else you want to say about five
uh nothing particular comes to mind
all right